Center for Inspired Teaching 'Real World History' Oral History Project 194
People's Archive, MLK Library
- Series 5: 2018-2019 School Year
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews, 2018
    - Joseph Harris interview, 2018-12; Harris, Joseph E., 1929-; Nikolas, Ferreyra
      Dr. Joseph Harris was born in Rocky Mount, North Carolina. He was raised by his great aunt and grew up attended segregated schools. Most young men in his town picked tobacco to make a living, but Dr. Harris looked to education as his way out, a way, his family emphasized, to "being somebody." He attended Hampton University for a year but because he could not afford to live on campus, he did not enjoy his experience there and went to work in Williamstown, Massachusetts, where his mother lived. After working as a cook at Williams College for a few years, Dr. Harris moved to Schenectady, New York, to work for General Electric. After saving up enough money, he moved to Washington, D.C., to complete his college education at Howard University where he received his undergraduate degree in 1952. While at Howard, Dr. Harris joined Reserve Officers' Training Corps (ROTC) and went into the service upon graduation. He served as an officer in the Korean War between 1952-1954 before returning to Howard to receive a Master's in African Studies in 1956. He then went on to earn a PhD from Northwestern University in Evanston, Illinois, where he met his wife. He completed his doctoral dissertation in Guinea, and later became a professor of history at Howard University.
      In this oral history interview, Dr. Joseph Harris, a long time D.C. resident, discusses his experiences moving from Rocky Mount, North Carolina, to Massachusetts, to Washington, D.C. He discusses his upbringing in Rocky Mount, attending Hampton University for a year, moving to Massachusetts, finishing college at Howard University, joining Reserve Officers' Training Corps (ROTC) and serving in the Korean War, and his academic career as a professor of African Studies.
    - Ruth Anne Lee Cohen interview, 2018-12; Cohen, Ruth Anne Lee; Isaac, Elijah
      Ruth Anne Lee Cohen was born in Savannah, Georgia, in the 1930s. She grew up with her parents, grandmother, and three younger siblings and by age five she was working in her grandmother's confectionary as a cashier. Ms. Cohen's parents and siblings moved to Detroit, Michigan, when she was in the seventh grade leaving her to live with her grandmother. Ms. Cohen attended a segregated Catholic school until seventh grade, at which point she enrolled at Alfred A. Beach High School where she met her husband. After finishing high school, Ms. Cohen attended Savannah State College (now Savannah State University) where she studied elementary education and graduated in 1958. After teaching in Savannah for three years, she moved north to join her husband in Washington. After serving overseas in the military, Ms. Cohen's husband refused to live in the South, and by the time they were married, he had already been living in Washington for a couple years. Ms. Cohen held off on joining him in D.C. until she had taught in Savannah public schools for three years, securing tenure. Once in Washington she continued teaching until her retirement in 1999. She took on other positions after retirement, such as the Business and Professional Women's League, helping students get scholarships to college.
      In this oral history interview, Ruth Anne Lee Cohen, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her life and experiences moving from Savannah, Georgia, to Washington, D.C. She discusses growing up in Savannah and educational experiences there, getting married, and teaching in D.C. until 1999. She talks about her favorite experiences teaching and from her life post-retirement.
  - Sub-Series 2: Indexes, 2018
    - Edith Crutchfield index, 2018-12-14; Crutchfield, Edith Amanda, 1936-; Ramos-Bracho, Isabella
    - Eva McLeod index, 2018-12-07; McLeod, Eva, 1918-; Washington, Kay; Alvarez, Steven
    - Jacqueline Hines index, 2018-12-28; Hines, Jacqueline, 1954-; Ayodeji, Oluwafunmilayo
      In this oral history interview, Jacqueline Hines, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her life and experiences moving from Wilson, North Carolina to Washington, D.C. She discusses her upbringing in Wilson, the reasons her family chose to move to D.C., her time at Ballou High School and Bowie State University, and her career as an educator and social worker. She also talks about issues she has faced since coming to Washington and some of the reasons she has never considered returning to North Carolina
    - James Jackson index, 2018-12-21; Jackson, James Lyde, 1936-; Diaz-Cruz, Saul
    - Joseph Harris index, 2018-12; Harris, Joseph E., 1929-; Nikolas, Ferreyra
    - Ruth Anne Lee Cohen index, 2018-12; Cohen, Ruth Anne Lee; Isaac, Elijah
  - Sub-Series 3: Transcripts, 2018
    - Edith Crutchfield transcript, 2018-12-14; Crutchfield, Edith Amanda, 1936-; Ramos-Bracho, Isabella
    - Eva McLeod transcript, 2018-12-07; McLeod, Eva, 1918-; Washington, Kay; Alvarez, Steven
    - Jacqueline Hines transcript, 2018-12-28; Hines, Jacqueline, 1954-; Ayodeji, Oluwafunmilayo
    - James Jackson transcript, 2018-12-21; Jackson, James Lyde, 1936-; Diaz-Cruz, Saul
    - Joseph Harris transcript, 2018-12; Harris, Joseph E., 1929-; Nikolas, Ferreyra
    - Ruth Anne Lee Cohen transcript, 2018-12; Cohen, Ruth Anne Lee; Isaac, Elijah
  - Sub-Series 4: Images
    - Annie Lee Jackson and Wallace Jackson, 1917 ca.
      An image of Annie Lee Jackson and Wallace Jackson, parents of James Jackson. Wallace Jackson is wearing a World War I military uniform.
      Jackson, Annie Lee; Jackson, Wallace
    - Butler School
      Exterior view of Butler School, a public school that served the Black community from 1921 to 1982.
    - Butler School historical marker
      A historical marker that reads 'Butler School, located on this site since 1921, was the second public school to serve Hartsville black community and operated for over sixty years. Known as the Darlington Co. Training School until 1939, it was renamed for Rev. Henry H. Butler, its principal 1909-1946. The first building on this site burned in 1961, extant buildings date from 1936 to the mid-1960s. Butler School was a junior high and high school when it closed in 1982.'
    - James Jackson high school graduation
      Formal graduation image of James Jackson.
      Jackson, James Lyde, 1936-
    - James Jackson
      James Jackson during an oral history interview.
    - Elijah Isaac and Ruth Anne Lee Cohen
      Elijah Isaac and Ruth Anne Lee Cohen pose for a photograph after completing and oral history interview.
      Cohen, Ruth Anne Lee; Isaac, Elijah
- Series 6: 2019-2020 School Year
  - Sub-series 1: Interviews, 2019-2020
    - Alvin Harris interview, 2020-01-11; rwhc_ohp_2019_005.wav; Harris, Alvin, 1958-; Speight, Jordan
      Alvin "Flooty" Harris was born on October 21, 1958, outside of Raleigh, North Carolina, and was the youngest of his parents' five children. His mother, Betty Jean Lyn Harris (b. 10/22/1932), raised Mr. Harris and his sibling as a single mother with the help of grandparents. The family migrated to Washington, DC, in 1966, when Mr. Harris was only 8 years old, and moved into the Hill East neighborhood of Southeast. Upon moving to Washington, Mr. Harris completed primary school education at Thomas B. Bryan Elementary School, attended Charles W. Eliot Junior High School, and went on to graduate from Eastern High School in 1977. Mr. Harris then completed a four-year carpentry apprenticeship through the Joint Carpentry Apprentice Committee and subsequently spent nine years working in construction. After leaving construction, Mr. Harris got a job as a carpenter working the federal government. Mr. Harris worked for the government until his retirement.
      Mr. Alvin Harris discusses his life and experiences moving from Raleigh, North Carolina to Washington, DC. Mr. Harris discusses his early life in Raleigh, his family's move to Southeast Washington, DC, and his upbringing and education in the city. He also discusses his life in Washington, his work as a carpenter and career in construction, and his transition to work for the federal government. Additionally, Mr. Harris talks about Marion Berry and "Chocolate City," and the crack epidemic in DC.
    - Bernice Pitts interview, 2020-01-07; rwhc_ohp_2019_006.wav; Pitts, Bernice, 1939-; McLean, Trejure; In this oral history interview, Bernice Pitts, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her life and experiences moving from Laurinburg, North Carolina to Washington, DC. Ms. Pitts discusses her upbringing in North Carolina and the farm work she did with her family before talking about her move to D.C. and the transition to city life. Ms. Pitts talks about finding work in the city, working for the government, and retiring after a workplace injury. She also reflects on raising her children and grandchildren and gives some advice to future generations.
      Bernice Pitts was born on April 13th, 1939, in Laurinburg, North Carolina, and was one of Mary Magdalena McCoy and Dan Mclean's ten children. After her mother died in childbirth, Ms. Pitts and her younger siblings were sent to live with relatives. In 1956, at the age of 17, Ms. Pitts moved to D.C. to stay with one of her older sisters. After initially working different jobs as a cook and housekeeper, Ms. Pitts secured a job doing custodial work for the federal government. After moving to Washington she also married her husband, Nathaniel Pitts, and had seven children. Eventually, Ms. Pitts was forced to stop working for the government after a workplace injury. Since that time she has worked in the home, spent time with her husband until his passing, and helped raise her grandchildren. Ms. Pitts has a passion for cooking and baking and now spends her days cooking cakes and spending time with family.
      African Americans; Black persons; Women; Migration, Internal
    - Claudia Lewis interview, 2019-11-25; rwhc_ohp_2019_007.wav; Lewis, Claudia, 1937-; Artemus, Michael; In this oral history interview, Claudia Lewis, discusses her life and experiences moving from Ridge Spring, South Carolina, to Washington, D.C. She reflects on her childhood in the South, her family's move to Washington in 1946, and her educational experiences in Washington. She also discusses her experiences with work, church, and family in DC, as well as her move to Prince George's County Maryland in 1992. This oral history interview was conducted by a DC high school student as part of a class assignment on the Great Migration in Real World History.
      Claudia Lewis (ne Claudia Johnson) was born September 30, 1937 in Ridge Spring, South Carolina. Ms. Lewis grew up on a farm in Ridge Spring with her parents, Charlie May Johnson and Ulysses Johnson, and six siblings. Though she was too young to do any serious farming, all of her siblings had to help operate the farm. In 1946, Ms. Lewis's father made the decision that the family would move up north to Washington, D.C. Upon arriving in D.C., the family lived on Howard Road SE, but they soon moved to Northeast Washington. Ms. Lewis attended the Birney School on Nichols Avenue SE (now Martin Luther King Jr. Avenue SE) for a few months upon arriving in Washington, but after moving to Northeast during her sixth-grade year, she attended Burrville Elementary and later Merritt Elementary School. She went on to attend Kelly Miller Junior High before graduating from McKinley High School in 1956. Ms. Lewis then went to New York for a time before returning to Washington to begin a job at the Department of the Navy. She married her husband Elton Lewis in December 1969. After beginning as a mail clerk with the Department of the Navy, Ms. Lewis later became a secretary and remained there for her whole career. In 1992 Ms. Lewis moved to Prince George's County Maryland. Ms. Lewis's husband passed away in 2014, and Ms. Lewis currently lives with her daughter in Maryland.
      African Americans; Black persons; Migration, Internal; Women
    - Deacon Clarence Haywood interview, 2020-01-05; Haywood, Clarence, Deacon, 1974-; Glazerman, Sameer
      In this oral history interview, Clarence Haywood, a long time D.C. resident, discusses his life and experiences moving from Camilla, Georgia, to Washington, D.C. Deacon Haywood talks about his upbringing and family life in Camilla, Georgia, race relations in Camilla, and how he came to the D.C. region after serving in the Navy. He also discusses his life in Washington, his 40-year career as a nurse, cultural differences between the D.C. region and the South, and how D.C. has changed since he first moved to the region.
      Deacon Clarence Haywood was born in 1947 in Camilla, Georgia, and he grew up with his mother, grandparents, and three younger siblings (two brothers and a sister). For a time they stayed with their father in Atlanta, GA, but they soon returned to Camilla to live with his mother's parents because of issues between his parents. His grandfather, Roy Caesar, was a well-known farmer in Mitchell County, Georgia, and his grandmother was a registered nurse in Camilla. His mother worked in a factory, but she was often battling illness and worked less hours than many of her colleagues. After graduating high school in 1965, Deacon Haywood served in the US Navy for four years. Upon leaving the service, he settled in D.C. and began working at the National Institute of Health (NIH) as a hospital corpsman. He had never visited to D.C. before, and he was the first of his family to migrate north. NIH then paid for him to attend Marymount University in Arlington, Virginia, and become a registered nurse. Upon graduating in 1975, he began a forty-year career in nursing. Deacon Haywood has been a deacon at New Bethel Church of God in Christ in Takoma Park, D.C., for over three decades.
    - Jacqueline Hines interview, 2019-11-13; Hines, Jacqueline, 1954-; Bellamy, Kiarra
      In this oral history interview, Jacqueline Hines, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her life and experiences moving from Wilson, North Carolina, to Washington, D.C. She reflects on her upbringing in the South, her life in Washington, and her career as an early childhood educator and social worker.
    - Lena Bradley interview, 2019-11-19; rwhc_ohp_2019_003.wav; Bradley, Lena Mae Bunch Townsend, 1929-; Campbell, Amora
      Lena Mae Bunch Townsend Bradley was born in Wilson County, North Carolina, July 20, 1929 to Adelina Bunch and James Henry Bynum. She lived there until the age of five, at which time she moved to Kenly, North Carolina, in Johnson County, attending the city public grade school from the first to the sixth grade. She attended high school in Selma, North Carolina and graduated in 1950. She stayed with an aunt in D.C. during the summers starting in 1946, getting a job taking care of a wealthy older White woman in the community, and after graduating she stayed in the city, becoming a beautician, joining Second Baptist Church in 1953 and marrying in 1956. She participated in beauty competitions and won awards, traveling extensively with her husband, all the while remaining a member of Second Baptist for over sixty-seven years.
      In this oral history interview, Lena Bradley, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her life and experiences moving from Kenly, North Carolina, to Washington, D.C. She reflects on her upbringing and education in the South as well as her life in Washington and career as a beautician.
    - Thelma D. Jones interview, 2019-11-27; rwhc_ohp_2019_004.wav; Jones, Thelma D., 1952-; Rogin, Lola
      Thelma D. Jones' work has been fundamental to civic and youth activism and raising awareness of breast health. She is an award-winning community activist, breast cancer survivor, advocate, and founder of the Thelma D. Jones Breast Cancer Fund. Diagnosed in 2007 with a rare (unknown primary) and aggressive form of breast cancer (HER2+), her treatment regimen included chemotherapy, surgery (lumpectomy) and radiation. Jones is a seasoned volunteer with the American Cancer Society (ACS) and the American Cancer Society Cancer Action Network (ACSCAN). In the former capacity she has spoken both locally and nationally, delivering the message of early detection, prevention, treatment and hope to thousands of women, men and young girls. As the former DC State Lead Ambassador for ACSCAN, Jones has lobbied both national and local public officials for funding of tobacco control and cancer research. In April 2010, she established the Thelma D. Jones Breast Cancer Fund Support Group, the signature program of the Thelma D. Jones Breast Cancer Fund in Southwest DC. Focusing primarily on the historically less served communities, the support group has contributed significantly to providing a safe and secure place for emotional support for breast cancer survivors and caretakers to discuss and share their journeys, hear a range of highly skilled speakers, acquire information and resources, and give voices to those who are struggling in silence with their diagnosis. Prior to becoming a cancer advocate, Jones retired from the World Bank Group after more than 33 years. As one of the principal founders of the World Bank's institutional outreach program, Jones served as a community outreach coordinator, carrying out the Bank's global poverty mission on a local level in the areas of education, volunteer management, homelessness, training and summer employment for youth, and community development. Recognized for her long-time civic activism and advocacy, Jones has been featured extensively in the media where she speaks candidly about her cancer journey and her desire to turn her challenge into an opportunity to help others. She is the recipient of numerous awards and recognitions, including the Mayor's Award for Community Service in the Category of Lifetime Achievement and the prestigious White House Champion of Change Award. In June 2016, Jones was selected by ACSCAN to represent the organization at the White House's Moonshot Summit, and in September, she was recognized with the 2016 State Lead Ambassador of the Year Award by ACSCAN. Jones holds an AAS Degree from Durham College, Durham, NC and is a graduate of Georgetown University Nonprofit Management Executive Certificate program, George Washington University DC Neighborhood College and Leadership Greater Washington 00'. She is also a graduate of the National Breast Cancer Coalition Project LEAD and Wesley Theological Seminary Heal the Sick Program. In addition, Jones is a founding member of both Black Benefactors, a giving circle, and Black Philanthropic Alliance, a membership organization. Since 1982, she has served on the board of the Southwest Neighborhood Assembly (SWNA) where she holds several leadership positions, including president, vice president, chair of the Nominating Committee (at least ten times), contributing writer for The Southwester, chair of both the Youth Activities Task Force and the History Task Force Black History Subcommittee. Grounded in her faith, Jones is a long-time member of St. Augustine's Episcopal Church on the Southwest Waterfront. She serves as a lay reader, member of the Altar Guild, and member of the executive team to organize annual events on Justice Thurgood Marshall, a former member of the church. Jones has one son, Jamal, grandson, Seneca, and Ozzie, her Shih Tzu. She enjoys reading, traveling, attending Jazz events, working with youth, and being a coordinating nexus of positive events. Thelma D. Jones also completed an oral history interview with the DC Oral History Collaborative Buzzard Point Oral History Project.
      In this oral history interview, Thelma D. Jones, a long time DC resident, discusses her life and experiences moving from Snow Hill, North Carolina, to Washington, D.C. Ms. Jones talks about her family life and upbringing in Snow Hill; her move to Washington after graduating from Durham College; and her life and work in DC. Ms. Jones also discusses some of the changes she's witnessed in Washington and the impact she's made on the city.
  - Sub-series 2: Indexes, 2019-2020
    - Alvin Harris index, 2020-01-11; rwhc_ohp_2019_005_ind.pdf; Harris, Alvin, 1958-; Speight, Jordan
    - Bernice Pitts index, 2020-01-07; rwhc_ohp_2019_006_ind.pdf; Pitts, Bernice, 1939-; McLean, Trejure; In this oral history interview, Bernice Pitts, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her life and experiences moving from Laurinburg, North Carolina to Washington, DC. Ms. Pitts discusses her upbringing in North Carolina and the farm work she did with her family before talking about her move to D.C. and the transition to city life. Ms. Pitts talks about finding work in the city, working for the government, and retiring after a workplace injury. She also reflects on raising her children and grandchildren and gives some advice to future generations.
    - Claudia Lewis index, 2019-11-25; rwhc_ohp_2019_007_ind.pdf; Lewis, Claudia, 1937-; Artemus, Michael; In this oral history interview, Claudia Lewis, discusses her life and experiences moving from Ridge Spring, South Carolina, to Washington, D.C. She reflects on her childhood in the South, her family's move to Washington in 1946, and her educational experiences in Washington. She also discusses her experiences with work, church, and family in DC, as well as her move to Prince George's County Maryland in 1992. This oral history interview was conducted by a DC high school student as part of a class assignment on the Great Migration in Real World History.
    - Deacon Clarence Haywood index, 2020-01-05; Haywood, Clarence, Deacon, 1974-; Glazerman, Sameer
    - Jacqueline Hines index, 2019-11-13; Hines, Jacqueline, 1954-; Bellamy, Kiarra
    - Lena Bradley index, 2019-11-19; rwhc_ohp_2019_003_ind.pdf; Bradley, Lena Mae Bunch Townsend, 1929-; Campbell, Amora
    - Thelma D. Jones index, 2019-11-27; rwhc_ohp_2019_004_ind.pdf; Jones, Thelma D., 1952-; Rogin, Lola
  - Sub-series 3: Transcripts, 2019-2020
    - Alvin Harris transcript, 2020-01-11; rwhc_ohp_2019_005_tra.pdf; Harris, Alvin, 1958-; Speight, Jordan
    - Bernice Pitts transcript, 2020-01-07; rwhc_ohp_2019_006_tra.pdf; Pitts, Bernice, 1939-; McLean, Trejure; In this oral history interview, Bernice Pitts, a long time D.C. resident, discusses her life and experiences moving from Laurinburg, North Carolina to Washington, DC. Ms. Pitts discusses her upbringing in North Carolina and the farm work she did with her family before talking about her move to D.C. and the transition to city life. Ms. Pitts talks about finding work in the city, working for the government, and retiring after a workplace injury. She also reflects on raising her children and grandchildren and gives some advice to future generations.
    - Claudia Lewis transcript, 2019-11-25; rwhc_ohp_2019_007_tra.pdf; Lewis, Claudia, 1937-; Artemus, Michael; In this oral history interview, Claudia Lewis, discusses her life and experiences moving from Ridge Spring, South Carolina, to Washington, D.C. She reflects on her childhood in the South, her family's move to Washington in 1946, and her educational experiences in Washington. She also discusses her experiences with work, church, and family in DC, as well as her move to Prince George's County Maryland in 1992. This oral history interview was conducted by a DC high school student as part of a class assignment on the Great Migration in Real World History.
    - Deacon Clarence Haywood transcript, 2020-01-05; Haywood, Clarence, Deacon, 1974-; Glazerman, Sameer
    - Jacqueline Hines transcript, 2019-11-13; Hines, Jacqueline, 1954-; Bellamy, Kiarra
    - Lena Bradley transcript, 2019-11-19; rwhc_ohp_2019_003_tra.pdf; Bradley, Lena Mae Bunch Townsend, 1929-; Campbell, Amora